Finding Aid for College of Engineering (University of Michigan) records 1860-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
College of Engineering (University of Michigan) records
1860-2010
1900-1980
University of Michigan. College of Engineering.
Records of the University of Michigan College of Engineering include histories, correspondence and topical files of deans; minutes of the executive and other committees; faculty records, including minutes of meetings and faculty biographies; miscellaneous student and alumni records; and photographs.
8781 Bimu C141 2
101 linear feet
3 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the College of Engineering (Donor No. 1884 ) in several accessions beginning in 1937. Printed material is received on a regular basis. (Donor no. 1884 )
The collection is open for research except as noted.
The Department of Engineering was established at the University of Michigan in 1858, four years after engineering courses were first offered. In 1871 Professor DeVolson Wood suggested that the Department of Engineering be separated from the Department of Literature, Science, and the Arts, but it was not until 1895 that such a separation occurred. In that year, the departments of civil, mechanical, and electrical engineering were organized into a distinct Department of Engineering and Professor Charles Ezra Greene was appointed dean. The department was to be governed by the faculty, with the dean handling admission of students. Mortimer Elwyn Cooley, a professor of mechanical engineering at the University since 1881, was appointed dean upon Greene's death in 1903 and took office in 1904. He served as dean until 1928 and was succeeded by Herbert Charles Sadler, a professor of naval architecture and marine engineering who had been on the University of Michigan faculty for thirty-nine years. Sadler resigned the deanship in 1937 and was followed by Henry Clay Anderson, a professor in the Mechanical Engineering Department. Anderson died in 1939 and was replaced by Ivan Charles Crawford, a civil engineer who had served as dean of the colleges of engineering at the University of Idaho and the University of Kansas. He was dean of the College of Engineering at Michigan from 1940 to 1951. The sixth dean of the college, George Granger Brown, held the post from 1951 to 1957. He was followed by Stephen S. Attwood, 1957-1965, Gordon Van Wylen, 1965-1972, and David V. Ragone, 1972-1980. Hansford W. Farris served as acting dean from 1980 until the 1981 appointment of James J. Duderstadt. Duderstadt resigned in 1986 to become provost and vice president for academic affairs for the university. He was succeeded as dean by Charles M. Vest, 1986-1989. Daniel E. Atkins, III, was interim dean from 1989 to 1990, Peter M. Banks served as dean from 1990 to 1996, and Stephen W. Director assumed the deanship in 1996.
In 1905 the Regents of the University approved the establishment of a chair of architecture in the Department of Engineering. With this decision, courses in architecture were once again made available. (In 1876-1877 William Le Baron Jenney had lectured as Professor of Architecture and Design in the new Department of Architecture and Design, which had been established in 1873 within the School of Mines. Due to a lack of funds, these courses were suspended in 1877. Jenney left the university in 1880, having fulfilled his obligations as architect for the university's new museum).
By 1913 the Department of Engineering had become the Departments of Engineering and Architecture. The title was changed in 1915 to the Colleges of Engineering and Architecture. In 1931 the College of Architecture became an independent unit.
In 1920, under the leadership of Dean Cooley, the Department of Engineering Research was formed as a means of promoting cooperation between the university, the state, and private industry. Through this department private industries sponsored research projects that would be conducted by College of Engineering faculty members. In addition to providing financial assistance, such projects enabled students and faculty members to engage in research of current interest in a wide variety of areas. Beginning in 1940, projects sponsored by the federal government were undertaken by the department and in 1948 the department was reorganized as the Engineering Research Institute. In 1957-1958 the Research Institute became an administrative unit of the university.
Before World War II the College of Engineering focused primarily on undergraduate education and on providing students with practical experience and skill. The many technological advances that occurred during and after the war prompted an increased emphasis on research and theory and a corresponding emphasis on graduate education. This shift was reflected in the development of research facilities on the North Campus beginning in the 1950s with the Cooley Laboratory. Technological advances also prompted changes in the curriculum and structure of the college. Some new departments were created, such as Nuclear Engineering. Other departments shifted their emphases; Aeronautical Engineering, for example, became Aerospace Engineering. The records reflect these developments as well as the broad changes which took place in the College of Engineering from its inception in the late nineteenth century up to the 1970s.
In the 1980s the College of Engineering continued to meet the technological challenges of the future through instruction, research, and development. Most of the college was relocated to North Campus in the early 1980s. This was followed by additional construction and renovation to house the college's major research initiatives, including the Center for Advanced Scientific Computation, created to study the applications of supercomputing, and the Center for Robotics and Integrated Manufacturing (CRIM), established in 1981 to examine the future needs of the modern manufacturing industry.
Funding was a major concern of the college in the 1980s. The tightened budgets of the previous decade resulted in increased faculty teaching loads and decreased research resources. The college sought to rectify this situation by appealing to the state for increased funding, attempting to keep the University of Michigan's College of Engineering on par with its peer institutions. As it looked toward the 1990s, the goals of the college, as stated in College of Engineering Briefing Material 1988-89 (Box 52, Folder: Briefing Materials), were twofold: first, "to establish preeminence in certain areas of special relevance to the state and region," such as manufacturing science and technology, machine intelligence, systems integration, and engineering design; and second, "to establish preeminence in certain areas of research and education of anticipated importance to the future of technology," including advanced optics and electronics, materials science and technology, information technology, and biotechnology.
By 1996, new programs had been added, most notably a Department of Biomedical Engineering and an Engineering Research Center for Reconfigurable Machining; the latter was chosen by the National Science Foundation to be the largest center in the country for basic research in manufacturing. The college also continued to increase its presence on North Campus, adding a carillon tower, the Robert H. Lurie Engineering Center, and a new library called the Media Union. The latter, shared with the schools of Architecture and Urban Planning, Music, and Art, was an ambitious project, described as a place where "new information technology will create a 'virtual' community of thinkers, allowing face-to-face dialogue and collaboration across thousands of miles".
Deans of the College of Engineering
1895-1903 Charles Ezra Greene
1903-1928 Mortimer E. Cooley
1927-1928 George W. Patterson, Acting Dean
1928-1937 Herbert Charles Sadler
1937-1939 Henry C. Anderson
1940-1951 Ivan C. Crawford
1951-1957 George Granger Brown
1957-1965 Stephen S. Attwood
1965-1972 Gordon Van Wylen
1972-1980 David V. Ragone
1980-1981 Hansford W. Farris, Acting Dean
1981-1986 James J. Duderstadt
1986-1989 Charles M. Vest
1989-1990 Daniel E. Atkins, III, Interim Dean
1990-1996 Peter M. Banks
1996- Stephen W. Director
The records of the College of Engineering have been received in a number of accession over the years. Continuing records series and subseries received in multiple accession have not been physically integrated. In this descriptive finding aid like materials have been brought together to the extent possible. The following summary contents list provides an overview of the records intellectual and physical organization.
Summary Contents List
Histories -- (box 1)
Dean's files Mortimer E. Cooley, 1904-1928 -- (boxes 1-11) Herbert C. Sadler, 1928-1936 -- (box 11) Henry C. Anderson, 1931-1951 -- (boxes 11-13) Ivan C. Crawford, 1940-1941 -- (box 14) Deans I.C. Crawford to D.V. Ragone, 1920-1979 [bulk dates: 1950-1972] -- (boxes 14-26) Deans' Administrative Files, 1940-1990 [bulk dates: 1950-1985] -- (boxes 52-55) Deans' Departmental Files, 1954-1991 [bulk dates: 1977-1989] -- (boxes 55-56) Deans' Topical Files, 1986-1990 (includes some earlier materials) -- (boxes 38-43) James J. Duderstadt, 1981-1985 -- (boxes 56-59, 93)
Associate Dean's Files Senior Associate Dean's Files 1980-1992 Departmental Files -- (boxes 44-45) Administrative Files -- (boxes 45-46) D.E. Atkins' Project Files, 1981-1989 -- (boxes 46-49) H.S. Fogler, 1978-1983 -- (boxes 59-60) M.J. Sinnott, 1967-1981 -- (boxes 60-61) C.M. Vest, 1981-1988 -- (boxes 43, 61-62) Ann Monterio, 1970-2001 (boxes 96-97
Committee Files General -- (boxes 12-26, 30, 39-40, 52, 73-75) Administrative Committee, 1946-1982 -- (box 73) Curriculum Committee, 1911-1925 and 1973-1988 -- (boxes 30, 39, 73-75) Discipline, Committee on, 1913-1923 -- (box 75) Executive Committee, 1936-1984 [some gaps] -- (boxes 27-28, 39, 75) Standing Committee, 1887-1983 -- (boxes 25, 28-30, 75-76) Strategic Planning Implementation Communication Committee -- (box 102)
Faculty (includes Faculty Meeting Minutes), 1876-1983 -- (boxes 21, 30-35, 38, 46, 68-69, 91)
Student and Alumni Records, 1895-1991 -- (boxes 35, 37, 43, 46, 76-82)
Visual Materials Photographs, ca.1860s-1996 -- (boxes 50, 82-83 94, 95 outsize) Videotape, 1974 -- (box 83)
Scrapbooks, 1918-1978 -- (box 82)
The College of Engineering records date from 1873 to 1996 and measure 94 linear feet. The records document the internal activities of the College of Engineering, both administrative and academic, the role of the college as a unit of the University of Michigan, and research developments and trends over the years. Correspondence, meeting minutes, reports, financial records, and other material reflect changing research interests within the field of engineering as well as the curriculum development that has accompanied technological advances. Of particular interest are the files relating to outside work by faculty members, a question of enduring concern within the college. The records reflect the relations of the College of Engineering with private industry, especially through the documentation of funding from outside sources and the involvement of professors in outside research.
Subjects:
Black Action Movement (University of Michigan); Engineering.; Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Industrial Technology Institute (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Industry and education.; Michigan. State Board of Registration for Architects, Professional Engineers, and Land Surveyors.; Michigan League.; Research.; University of Michigan. Center for Research on Integrated Manufacturing.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science.; University of Michigan. Experimental Research in Electronic Submission Project.; University of Michigan. Engineering Research Institute.; University of Michigan. Institute of Science and Technology.; University of Michigan. Minority Engineering Program Office.; University of Michigan--Research.Research.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; World War, 1914-1918.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Anderson, Henry Clay, 1872-1939.; Atkins, Daniel E. (Daniel Ewell); Attwood, Stephen S. (Stephen Stanley), 1897-1965.; Brown, George Granger, 1896-; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Crawford, Ivan Charles, 1886-1960.; Greene, Charles E. (Charles Ezra), 1842-1903.; Ragone, David V., 1930-; Sadler, Herbert Charles, 1872-; Van Wylen, Gordon John.; Vest, Charles M.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Astronomical observatories.; Coal mining.; Engineering.; Laboratories.; Mining.; Peach Mountain Radio Astronomy Observatory (Mich.); Unionville (Mich.); University of Michigan. College of Engineering.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Histories
  Several unpublished histories of the College of Engineering and individual departments,as well as a variety of historical notes and documents have been brought together at the beginning of the records to form the Histories series.
  - History of the Department of Mechanical Engineering, 1881-1937; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - History of the College of Engineering by Mortimer Cooley, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Historical Information, 1936-1972 (Box 1)
- Dean's Files, 1904-1991
  The Dean's Files series (41 linear feet) comprises the bulk of the record group, spanning the years 1904 to 1991, and includes the records of Deans Cooley, Sadler, Anderson, Crawford, Brown, Attwood, Van Wylen, Ragone, Duderstadt, Vest and Atkins.
  - Mortimer E. Cooley
    The subseries Mortimer E. Cooley Correspondence Files and Herbert C. Sadler Correspondence Files are arranged chronologically, and, although consisting primarily of correspondence, they do include occasional reports and financial statements. Cooley's extensive correspondence (ca. 10 feet) with members of the college, prospective students, engineering graduates seeking employment, and engineering firms reflects the intimate involvement of Cooley in the administration of the College of Engineering, but also his continued interest in the more technical aspects of engineering, as is evident in his correspondence with manufacturers and engineers regarding equipment for the various departments. The files occasionally reflect the impact of larger events on affairs within the College of Engineering. For example, a series of letters written by professors and by engineering firms in 1918 concerns the question of whether or not to institute an intensive summer course to train women as draftsmen in order to fill shortages created by the war.
    - Correspondence File
      - Undated, 4 folders (Box 1)
      - January-December 1904, 21 folders (Box 1)
      - January-November 1905, 36 folders (Box 2)
      - December 1905-August 1907, 29 folders (Box 3)
      - September 1907-January 1909, 30 folders (Box 4)
      - February 1909-December 1910, 29 folders (Box 5)
      - January 1911-May 1913, 31 folders (Box 6)
      - June 1913-January 1916, 36 folders (Box 7)
      - February 1916-May 1919, 41 folders (Box 8)
      - June 1919-August 1922, 39 folders (Box 9)
      - September 1922-January 1926, 41 folders (Box 10)
      - February 1926-June 1928, 25 folders (Box 11)
  - Herbert Charles Sadler
    - Correspondence File
      - July 1928-December 1936, 19 folders (Box 11)
  - Henry C. Anderson
    The records of Henry C. Anderson are divided into two subseries: Henry C. Anderson Correspondence Files, arranged chronologically, and Henry C. Anderson Topical Files, arranged alphabetically by subject. The topical files not only document Anderson's activities as dean, but also his work throughout the 1930s in various capacities: as chairman of the State Board of Registration for Architects, Engineers, and Surveyors (1937-1939), and as a participant in such university organizations as a member of the Board in Control of Athletics, the Board in Control of Religious Activities, and the board of the Alumni Association. Minutes of these bodies are included, as well as a complete run of minutes of the Board of Governors of the Michigan League for the period from December 1931 to 1939.
    - Correspondence File
      - January-December 1937, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - January 1938-December 1939, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Topical Files
      - Accelerated Program, 1941-1942 (Box 12)
      - Aeronautical Research Center, 1947-1951 (Box 12)
      - Alumni Association, 1933-1939; 3 folders (Box 12)
      - Alumni Association: Alumnae Council (Box 12)
      - Board in Control of Athletics, 1931-1934 (Box 12)
      - Board in Control of Physical Education, 1934-1939; 3 folders (Box 12)
      - Board in Control of Religious Activities (Box 12)
      - Board of Registration for Architects, Engineers, and Surveyors, 1937-1939; 4 folders (Box 12)
      - Bureau of Appointments Advisory Committee, 1932-1937 (Box 12)
      - Coal, Committee on, 1935-1937 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, Miscellaneous, A-F, 7 folders (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, Miscellaneous, G-Z, 15 folders (Box 13)
      - Faculty Research Fund, 1933-1937 (Box 13)
      - Graduate School, Executive Board, 1932-1937 (Box 13)
      - Housing Committee (Box 13)
      - Intrafraternity Council, 1936-1937 (Box 13)
      - Jubilee, 1936-1937 (Box 13)
      - Men's Council (Box 13)
      - Michigan League, Board of Governors, 1931-1939; 4 folders (Box 13)
      - Michigan Union, 1932-1938; 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Outside Relations, Committee on (Box 13)
      - Peace Council (Box 13)
      - Plant and Equipment, Committee on, 1932-1933 (Box 13)
      - Speeches (Box 13)
  - Ivan C. Crawford and Successors
    The subseries Ivan C. Crawford Correspondence Files is very small (2 folders), and supplements the larger subseries Ivan C. Crawford and Successors Topical Files (13 linear feet). This subseries contains topical files from the deanships of Crawford through Ragone and is arranged alphabetically. It provides documentation of the wide-ranging activities of the various departments within the College of Engineering. (It should be noted that there is a gap in the topical files; no folders were received for the letters I through L.) These files pertain more clearly to the work of the dean in administering the College of Engineering than do Anderson's topical files. Of particular interest are the early annual reports and advisory board minutes of the Department of Engineering Research and records of its successor, the Engineering Research Institute, from the 1930's to the 1950's. Although some of these folders predate Crawford's years as dean, they have been included here because they provide background information for the later records. Other notable files include the annual reports of the Cooley Memorial Laboratory; accreditation reports; and the files regarding Consulting, which consists of questionnaires in which engineering professors indicated the number of days spent doing consulting work in that academic year and the companies for which they worked. The Department Reviews files include committee reports on conditions within the departments and letters from faculty members evaluating their departments.
    Finally, the Communications with Regents files consists for the most part of requests for sabbaticals and sick leave and resolutions regarding faculty appointments.
    - Correspondence File
      - 1940-1941, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Topical Files
      - Academic Affairs, Vice President for (Box 14)
      - Academic Data Procedures, Committee for the Study of (Box 14)
      - Accreditation: Engineers Council for Professional Development (ECPD)
        - 1929-1940 (Box 14)
        - 1948-1974, 15 folders (Box 14)
        - 1977-1978 (Box 14)
      - Aeronautical Engineering 50th Anniversary (1964) (Box 15)
      - Aerospace Building, 1967-1972 (Box 15)
      - American Society for Engineering Education-Goals, 1962-1968 (Box 15)
      - Annual Report, College of Engineering, 1957/58-1963/64; 7 folders (Box 15)
      - Annual Report, College of Engineering, 1966/67-1969/70; 4 folders (Box 15)
      - Apollo, 1969 (Box 15)
      - The Arch, 1964-1967 (Box 15)
      - Arendt, Hannah, November 1968 (Box 15)
      - Atmospheric and Oceanic Science Department, 1971-1976 (Box 15)
      - Automotive Engineering Laboratory, 1951-1959; 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Bioengineering, 1968-1972; 4 folders (Box 15)
      - Black Action Movement (BAM) Strike
        - Alumni Response (Box 15)
        - Alumni Response (cont.), 2 folders (Box 16)
        - Correspondence (Box 16)
        - Flyers (Box 16)
        - Newspaper Articles (Box 16)
        - Reports (Box 16)
        - Statements (Box 16)
      - Brown, George Granger, 1920-1967 (scattered) (Box 16)
      - Budget, 1965/66-1972/73; 11 folders (Box 16)
      - Buildings, 1955-1973 (Box 16)
      - Bureau of the Budget, 1958 (Box 16)
      - Calendar Committee, 1967-1969 (Box 16)
      - Camp Davis, 1955-1964 (Box 16)
      - Capital Outlay Program, 1954 (Box 16)
      - Capital Outlay Program, 1955-1960; 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Centennial of Engineering
        - Biographical Sketches of Faculty (Box 17)
        - Citations (Box 17)
        - Committees (Box 17)
        - Convocation and Other Programs (Box 17)
        - Correspondence (Box 17)
        - Final Report (Box 17)
        - Finances (Box 17)
        - Movie, 3 folders (Box 17)
        - Newspaper Clippings (Box 17)
        - Notes by Stephen Attwood (Box 17)
        - Radio Script (Box 17)
      - Chemical and Metallurgical Department, 1953-1971 (Box 17)
      - Chemical Engineering Department, 1971-1976 (Box 17)
      - Chrysler Center for Continuing Engineering Education, 1965-1971; 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Chrysler Engineering Graduate School Yearbook, 1932 (Box 17)
      - Chrysler Institute, 1934-1959 (scattered) (Box 17)
      - Civil Engineering, ca., 1955-1977 (Box 17)
      - Classified Research, 1967-1970; 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Claybourn, John G., 1966-1969 (Box 17)
      - Commencement, 1962-1970 (Box 17)
      - Commission on Engineering Education, 1964-1965 (Box 17)
      - Committees, 1957-1968 (Box 17)
      - Compensation Policy, 1964-1967 (Box 18)
      - Computer, Information and Control Engineering, 1952-1968 (Box 18)
      - Computer Project, 1959-1966 (Box 18)
      - Consulting:, 1972
        - Aerospace Engineering (Box 18)
        - Atmospheric and Oceanic Science (Box 18)
        - Chemical Engineering (Box 18)
        - Civil Engineering (Box 18)
        - Electrical and Computer Engineering (Box 18)
        - Engineering Mechanics (Box 18)
        - Humanities (Box 18)
        - Industrial and Operations Engineering (Box 18)
        - Materials and Metallurgical Engineering (Box 18)
        - Mechanical Engineering (Box 18)
        - Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering (Box 18)
        - Nuclear Engineering (Box 18)
      - Consumers Power Company-Commonwealth Associates Project, 1966-1967 (Box 18)
      - Convair, 1956-1957 (Box 18)
      - Convocation, 1962-1967 (Box 18)
      - Cooley Electronics Laboratory, 1953-1969; 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Cooley Electronics Laboratory Annual Reports, 1961-1969 (Box 18)
      - Cooley Foundation, 1956-1971 (scattered) (Box 18)
      - Cooley Foundation Committee, 1936-1954 (Box 18)
      - Cooley Memorial Building, 1953-1958 (Box 18)
      - Core Courses, 1966-1968 (Box 18)
      - Curriculum Committee, 1957-1976; 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Dean's Page Michigan Technic, 1957-1966 (scattered) (Box 18)
      - Deanship Committee, 1957; 1964 (Box 18)
      - Dearborn Center, 1956-1967 (Box 18)
      - Dearborn Center: Executive Committee Minutes, 1959-1963 (Box 17)
      - Defense Analyses, Institute for, 1956-1959 (Box 18)
      - Degrees, 1963-1976 (Box 18)